Finding Aid for Albert B. Cleage Jr. papers, 1949-2005
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Shrines of the Black Madonna National Office (Detroit)
  The Shrine of the Black Madonna National Office series consists of two separately maintained topical files, covering the period of 1968 to 1973 and 1977 to 1979. These files provide a glimpse into how the Shrines worked on a day-to-day basis, and how the Council of Cardinals exerted its influence over the direction of the movement on both a national and regional level, as well as on the personal lives of BCN members. This series also includes publications of the Shrines organization relating to the Black Christian Nationalist movement. In addition to programs from their annual conventions, this set of files includes policies and procedures, basic doctrinal statements, information for new members, a Bible study workbook, and history background of the church.
  - Topical files 1977-1979
    (Includes some earlier material)
    - 1977
      - Chanza reports and minutes (Box 8)
      - Cultural Center and other reports (Box 8)
    - 1978
      - Administration Minutes (Box 9)
      - Alkebu-lan Academy Minutes (Box 9)
      - Alkebu-lan Nursery, Nursery Staffing (Box 9)
      - ATG 1 MOR Fact Sheet (Box 9)
      - Black Christian Nationalism Study Guide (Box 9)
      - Central Index (Box 9)
      - Chanza Minutes and Reports, 2 folders (Box 9)
      - Choir Report (Box 9)
      - Communal Budget Listing (Box 9)
      - COR Reports (Box 9)
      - Cultural Center #2 Bi-Weekly Reports (Box 9)
      - Disciplinary Action (Box 9)
      - Executive Council Meeting (Box 9)
      - Financial Procedures (Box 9)
      - Group Transfers and Reorganization (Box 9)
      - Group Meetings (Box 9)
      - Houston Cadre Encounter (Box 9)
      - Institutional Reports (Box 9)
      - Kalamazoo Finance Reports (Communal Budget) (Box 9)
      - Maccabee Daily Highlights (Box 9)
      - Missionary Outreach Interdepartmental Communications (Box 9)
      - MOR Minutes (Box 9)
      - Music Department (Box 9)
      - Security Report for Administrative Council (Box 9)
      - Shrine #1 MOR Behavioral Fact Sheet (Box 9)
      - Shrine #7 Kalamazoo (Box 9)
      - Shrine #10 Houston (Box 9)
      - Switchboard Operator's Report Administration Meeting (Box 9)
      - Transportation -- Nation Fleet (Box 9)
      - Treasurer's Reports (Weekly) (Box 9)
    - 1979
      - Alkebu-lan Academy Memos (Box 9)
      - Alkebu-lan Nursery (Box 9)
      - Chanza Process (Box 9)
      - Chanza Reports
        - Shrine #1 (Box 9)
        - Shrine #2 (Box 9)
        - Shrine #3 (Box 9)
      - Chanza Minutes (Box 9)
      - Communal Budget (Box 9)
      - COR
        - Communication (Box 9)
        - Reports (Box 9)
      - Kitchen (Box 9)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 9)
      - MOR
        - Securing Trips (Box 9)
        - Out of Town Teams (Box 9)
        - Goals and Quotas (Box 9)
        - Communications (Box 9)
  - Topical File 1968-1973
    - Accord, Inc. 1968-1969, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Action Council Organizing Committee 1969-1970 (Box 9)
    - Action Group Meetings (Monthly) 1968, 1971-1972 (Box 9)
    - African-American Teacher's Association (Box 9)
    - African World Bookshelf 1969 (Box 9)
    - Afro-America, Inc. (Yale University) 1970 (Box 9)
    - Alice Strauther Memorial Committee 1969-1970 (Box 9)
    - American Civil Liberties Union 1970-1972 (Box 9)
    - American Orthopsychiatric Association, Inc. 1970 (Box 9)
    - Archdiocese of Detroit 1969 (Box 9)
    - BCN Leadership Cadre 1970 (Box 9)
    - Benevolent and Protective Order Constitution 1968 (Box 9)
    - Black Action Movement (University of Michigan) 1970 (Box 9)
    - Black Action Training, Irv Joiner 1970 (Box 9)
    - Black Affairs Council 1969 (Box 9)
    - Black Christian Nationalist Convention 1970 (Box 9)
    - Black Christian Nationalist Convention (Second) 1971 (Box 9)
    - Black Christian Nationalist Convention Correspondence 1970 (Box 10)
    - Black Christian Nationalist Marriage Service (Box 10)
    - Black Christian Nationalist Student Movement (High School Level) 1970-1972 (Box 10)
    - Black Heritage Tea 1970-1971 (Box 10)
    - Black Media List (Box 10)
    - Black Messiah 1968 (Box 10)
    - Black Nationalism (Box 10)
    - Black Star Market 1968 (Box 10)
    - Black Studies -- Graduate Studies 1971 (Box 10)
    - Black Teacher's Caucus 1970 (Box 10)
    - Board of National Missions 1969 (Box 10)
    - Board of Education 1968-1973 (Box 10)
    - Book Reviews (Box 10)
    - Book -- Quest for a Black Theology 1970-1971 (Box 10)
    - Campaign Literature 1970 (Box 10)
    - Charge to New Members and Libation (Box 10)
    - Chicago Theological Seminary 1969 (Box 10)
    - Choir 1970 (Box 10)
    - Christian Century -- Dean Peerman 1971 (Box 10)
    - Colgate Divinity School -- Rochester, New York 1968-1970 (Box 10)
    - Columbia Radio and Television 1968-1969 (Box 10)
    - Commission for Racial Justice -- Cobb 1968-1971 (Box 10)
    - Commission on Religion and Race -- United Methodist Church 1969-1970 (Box 10)
    - Commitment Campaign 1970 (Box 10)
    - Communications 1971 (Box 10)
    - Congress of African People 1971 (Box 10)
    - Co-op Buying 1971 (Box 10)
    - Core 1971-1972 (Box 10)
    - Cornell University 1969 (Box 10)
    - Contracts on Books 1970 (Box 10)
    - Detroit Free Press -- Hiley Ward 1969 (Box 10)
    - Detroit Industrial Mission 1968 (Box 10)
    - Detroit Metropolitan Association of the United Church of Christ 1968-1969 (Box 10)
    - Detroit Metropolitan Association 1970-1973 (Box 10)
    - Draft Information -- Selective Service, etc. 1969-1975 (Box 10)
    - Duke University 1970-1973 (Box 10)
    - Economic Development Corporation 1969-1970 (Box 10)
    - Elmhurst College 1968 (Box 10)
    - Federation 1967 (Box 10)
    - Fisk University 1969 (Box 10)
    - Fites Bottom Improvement Campaign 1968 (Box 10)
    - Garrett Theological Seminary -- Rev. Hycel Taylor 1971 (Box 10)
    - Graymoor Ecumenical Institute 1969 (Box 10)
    - Heidelberg College 1968-1969 (Box 10)
    - Heritage Committee (Box 10)
    - Inner City Organizing Committee 1968 (Box 10)
    - IFCO 1968-1970 (Box 10)
    - In-Service Ministerial Training Program 1970 (Box 10)
    - Joint Strategy and Action Committee 1970 (Box 10)
    - Legal Aid 1967-1968 (Box 10)
    - Letters from Inmates 1967-1972 (Box 10)
    - Macomb County Community College 1970 (Box 10)
    - Martin Luther King, Jr. Memorial Library and Center 1968-1970 (Box 10)
    - Men's Club 1969-1971 (Box 10)
    - Methodist Grants -- Bishop Loder 1969 (Box 10)
    - Michigan Conference -- Duane Vore 1974 (Box 10)
    - Michigan Conference of the United Church of Christ 1969-1971 (Box 10)
    - Michigan State University 1968 (Box 10)
    - Mini Shopping Centers 1969-1970
      - General (Box 10)
      - National Board (Box 10)
      - Areas (Box 10)
    - Ministers for Racial and Social Justice (Rev. Edmonds) 1969-1971 (Box 10)
    - Minutes of Meetings 1969 (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous Handouts and Literature 1969 (Box 10)
    - Miss Black America Beauty Pageant 1970 (Box 10)
    - Morris, Ronald -- Norfolk State College 1971 (Box 10)
    - Morrow and Company, Inc. Publishers 1971-1972
      - Dan Johnson (Box 10)
      - Book Reviews (Box 10)
    - National Association of Black Students 1970 (Box 10)
    - National Conference of Friends 1968-1969 (Box 10)
    - National Committee of Black Churchmen 1968-1971 (Box 10)
    - National Council of the Churches of Christ -- Delta Ministry 1970-1971 (Box 10)
    - National Staff Requests 1972 (Box 10)
    - National Training Center (Box 10)
    - NCC (Charles Spivey) Department of Social Justice 1969-1970 (Box 10)
    - News Media 1968 (Box 10)
    - Newsome, Dr. Moses 1970 (Box 10)
    - Norfolk Committee for the Improvement of Education, Inc. 1970 (Box 10)
    - North Carolina Central University 1970-1971 (Box 10)
    - Oakland Community College 1969 (Box 10)
    - Oberlin College 1969-1972 (Box 10)
    - Ohio State University 1969-1971 (Box 10)
    - Ohio Wesleyan University 1970 (Box 10)
    - Order of Chaka 1968 (Box 10)
    - PAC (Pan-African Congress, USA) 1970-1972 (Box 10)
    - Panther's Den Youth Organization 1969-1970 (Box 10)
    - Parsons, Donald 1971 (Box 10)
    - Permission for Publication 1970 (Box 10)
    - Plymouth Congregational Church (Kalamazoo-Grand Rapids) 1970 (Box 10)
    - Political 1968 (Box 10)
    - Princeton Theological Seminary 1969 (Box 10)
    - Procedures, policies, etc. (Box 10)
    - Rand McNally and Company 1969 (Box 10)
    - Random House 1970 (Box 10)
    - Republic of New Africa 1970-1972 (Box 10)
    - Reviews 1972 (Box 10)
    - Ripon College 1969-1970 (Box 10)
    - Second Book Correspondence 1970 (Box 10)
    - Saint John's Congregational Church, Massachusetts 1969 (Box 10)
    - Saint John's United Church of Christ 1969 (Box 10)
    - Sanford, Warner 1970 (Box 10)
    - Sarah Lawrence College 1970 (Box 10)
    - School of Black Studies 1970 (Box 10)
    - Security and Safety for Nation Proposal 1968 (Box 10)
    - Seminary Students 1969 (Box 10)
    - Sheed and Ward, Inc. 1968-1971 (Box 10)
    - Southern Regional Newsletter, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Financial Drives 1979
    - New Regional Drive (Box 11)
    - Last Chance Drive (Box 11)
    - Born Again Drive (Box 11)
    - First Step Drive (Box 11)
    - Anniversary Drive (Box 11)
    - Holy Crusade Drive (Box 11)
  - BCN Interdepartmental Communications 1980-1983 (Box 11)
  - BCN Official Publications (Box 11)
  - 2nd Annual "Spring Forum Series" 1970
    - Basics of BCN 1972 (Box 11)
      (include policies, Creed, regulations)
    - Basics of BCN for Membership 1993 (Box 11)
    - BCN Catalogue 1973-1974 (Box 11)
    - Bible Study Student Workbook no. 4, The Pre-Christian Era 1995 (Box 11)
    - Books of prayers 1989-1991 & undated (Box 11)
    - Central Congregational Church publications (Box 11)
    - Church History Presentation 1993 (Box 11)
    - Closer: Weekly Accountability Report, September November 1997 (Box 11)
    - Convention Program (Biennial)
      - 1972 (Box 11)
      - 1975 (Box 11)
    - Honoring Rev. Albert B. Cleage, Jr. 1963 (Box 11)
    - KUA Group Devotionals (Box 11)
    - National Pan African Synod programs
      - 1993 (Box 11)
      - 1996 (Box 11)
      - 2000 (Box 11)
    - Shrine #10 (Houston), 10th Anniversary 1987 (Box 11)
    - Shrine #10 (Houston), 15th Anniversary 1992 (Box 11)
    - Shrine of the Black Madonna
      - 30th Anniversary calendar 1983 (Box 11)
      - 40th Anniversary Program 1993 (Box 11)
      - 50th Anniversary Jubilee 2003 (Box 11)
    - Shrine of the Black Madonna Cultural Center & Book Store review
      - December 1992 (Box 11)
      - August 1995 (Box 11)
    - Signs and Symbols guides 1994, 2002 (Box 11)
    - Spiritual Retreat Handbooks 1994, 1995 (Box 11)
- Sound recordings
  The Sound Recordings series consists of two music phonograph records (45 rpm) and ten compact discs. The CDs are of Jaramogi Abebe Agyeman (Albert Cleage Jr.) teaching and preaching. Of note are two separate tributes given following the assassinations of Malcolm X (1967) and Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. (1968).
  - Messages by Jaramogi Abebe Agyeman, compact discs
    - What Carol Shall We Sing? December 25, 1966 (Box 11)
    - Tribute to Malcolm X February 26, 1967 (Box 11)
    - Tribute to Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. April 7, 1968 (Box 11)
    - Individualism September 18, 1976 (Box 11)
    - An Introduction to BCN Theology (Operant Conditioning) August 5, 1984 (Box 11)
    - The Messianic Community February 16, 1986 (Box 11)
    - The Anointment of Jesus December 6, 1987 (Box 11)
    - The New Black Reality, 1st in series June 16, 1991 (Box 11)
    - The Global Reality, 2nd in series June 23, 1991 (Box 11)
    - The Role of the Black Mother in the Black Nation 1980s undated (Box 11)
  - Phonograph records
    - Performance of Bro. John Ware: Side 1, Jesus When Trouble Burdens; Side 2, Without God, 45 rpm (Box 11)
    - Sound of Soul Combo: Side 1, A Camel's Walk, Part I; Side 2, A Camel's Walk, Part II (Box 11)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series includes portraits, photos of Cleage preaching, church events and related activities. Many of the photos are undated and unidentified.
  - Portraits, church events, buildings, etc. (Box 11)
  - Classrooms, portraits, church events, etc. (Box 11)
  - Cleage in pulpit preaching, miscellaneous (Box 12)
    (This folder was not microfilmed)
- Miscellaneous
  The Miscellaneous series includes clippings and copies of newspapers and other publications with references to Cleage and his ministry. This material has not been microfilmed
  - Clippings, newspapers, etc. (Box 12)